Guide to the Radio Haiti Papers, circa 1934-2003, bulk 1968-2003 RL.11499
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Culture and History, 1968-2003
  - Language, 1998-2003
    - Francophonie, 1998-2003; 1 folder (Box 22)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to Francophonie, including texts by Michel-Philippe Lerebours and Roger Gaillard.
    - Linguistics and Language, 1999-2001; 1 folder (Box 23)
      See also: Education; Literacy
      Radio Haiti materials relating to linguistics and language, including a linguistics colloquium and International Creole Day.
  - National Heritage, 1973-2002
    - 250th anniversary of Port-au-Prince, 1999-2000; 1 folder (Box 23)
      See also: Carnaval; ISPAN; Monuments
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the commemoration of the 250th anniversary of Port-au-Prince and restoration of public spaces and monuments. Includes conflict between the Commission pour la Commémoration du 250è Anniversaire de Port-au-Prince and Carnaval organizers over use of the Champ-de-Mars.
    - Archives Nationales, 1977-2002; 1 folder (Box 23)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to Haiti's National Archives. Includes press, director Wilfrid Bertrand's appearances on Radio Haiti.
    - Citadelle, 1977-1999; 2 folders (Box 23)
      Radio Haiti and external materials relating to the restoration and preservation of the Citadelle Laferriére and Sans-Souci palace. External materials include brochures, guidebooks, maps, photographs of the 1980 reconstruction, press releases, reports. Also includes 1978 Le Nouvelliste article about a painting of Henry Christophe by British painter Richard Evans.
    - Haitian Revolution, bicentennial, 1983-2002; 1 folder (Box 23)
      See also: ISPAN, Monuments; Citadelle
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to commemorations of the Haitian Revolution, the bicentennial of Haiti. Includes commemorations of the deaths of Toussaint Louverture and Jean-Jacques Dessalines, repatriation of Toussaint's ashes.
    - History, general, 1973; 1984; 1998-2002; 1 folder (Box 23)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials, including information onf Serge Fourcand's ENTRE LE VICE ET LA VIOLENCE on Haiti from 1971-1975, Lucienne Hertelou Estimé's book about her husband Dumarsaid Estimé, a document on Benoît Batraville, and pirate ships. Also includes 1973 Le Nouvelliste article about commemorations of Rosalvo Bobo in Cap Haïtien, Dany Laferrière's 1984 essay about Roger Gaillard in Haïti Observateur, and Jean Dominique's notes on the 70th anniversary of the death of Benoît Batraville.
    - ISPAN, monuments, etc., 1977-2001; 1 folder (Box 23)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the restoration, preservation, and commemoration of monuments and other important sites of national heritage. Includes materials relating to ISPAN (Institut de Sauvegarde du Patrimoine National), the 1989 vandalism against Jean-René Jérôme's Marchaterre monument, statues and portraits of revolutionary leaders, gingerbread houses, Fort Jacques, Crête à Pierrot, and various monuments.
    - Libraries, 1991-2001; 1 folder (Box 23)
      Radio Haiti materials relating to libraries, including the Bibliothèque Nationale and other libraries.
    - MUPANAH, 1995-1999; 1 folder (Box 23)
      Radio Haiti materials and external press relating to the Musée du Panthéon National Haïtien (MUPANAH), the national heritage museum in Port-au-Prince.
    - Slavery and slave trade, 1991-2001; 1 folder (Box 23)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials on commemorations of slavery and the slave trade.
  - Religion, 1983-2003
    - Bois Caïman, 1991-1999; 1 folder (Box 23)
      See also: Vodou; Protestants
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about Bois Caïman, where Boukman led a Vodou ceremony in 1791 that began the Haitian Revolution. Includes the commemoration of the 200th anniversary of the ceremony (1991) and the conflicts that took place when American and Haitian Protestants attempted to "convert" Bois Caïman and replace the vodou influence with Christianity (1997, 1998).
    - Carnaval, 1998-2003; 4 folders (Box 24)
      Radio Haiti materials relating to Carnaval, including security, violence, finances, and activities in the Haitian provinces. Includes the fatal accident on the RAM float in 1998 that killed five people including political activist Gérard Laforêt, and conflicts over use of the Champ-de-Mars in 2000.
    - Fèt Gede, 1998-2001; 1 folder (Box 24)
      Radio Haiti materials relating to Fèt Gede (Guédé), the Day of the Dead in Haitian Vodou.
    - Fêtes Patronales, 1991-2002; 2 folders (Box 24)
      See also: Rara; Carnaval; Vodou; National Calendar
      Radio Haiti materials relating to various "fêtes patronales", saint days, regional festivals, pilgrimages, and Easter throughout Haiti, including Saut d'Eau.
    - Rara, 1989-2001; 1 folder (Box 24)
      See also: Fêtes Patronales, Carnaval, Vodou
      Radio Haiti materials relating to Rara, the street music and parades that typically take place during Easter week.
    - Religion, general, 1998-2000; 1 folder (Box 24)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to religion and religious celebrations (including Catholics, Evangelical Christians, Haitian Muslims).
    - Vodou, 1983-2001; 2 folders (Box 24)
      See also: Bois Caïman, Rara, Fêtes Patronales
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials on vodou. Includes open letters and press releases from grassroots organizations, particularly Zantray; dechoukaj of vodou practitioners in the late 1980s, among other topics.
  - Sports, 1978-2003
    - Radio Haiti correspondence, 1999; 1 folder (Box 24)
      Letters from Radio Haiti to potential sponsors of the station's coverage of the Panamerican Games, and to Teleco regarding collaborating to broadcast the national soccer championship. Includes letterhead and Radio Haiti stamps.
    - SEJSSC, 1995-2001; 1 folder (Box 24)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials (decrees and press releases) relating to the Secrétariat d'Etat à la jeunesse, aux sports et au service civique (SEJSSC).
    - Soccer, 2000-2002; 1 folder (Box 24)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to soccer, including the Fédération Haïtienne de Football, Haitian national championship, World Cup 2002, men's and women's soccer, the Caribbean Cup, FIFA.
    - Soccer, 1999; 1 folder (Box 25)
      Radio Haiti materials (including scripts and match sheets) and external materials relating to soccer, including the Fédération Haïtienne de Football, Haitian national championship.
    - Soccer, 1998; 1 folder (Box 25)
      Radio Haiti materials (including scripts and match sheets) and external materials relating to soccer, including the Fédération Haïtienne de Football and the government's decision to dissolve the Federation, under-17 soccer, and the national championship.
    - Soccer, 1978; 1979; 1991; 1995-1997; undated; 1 folder (Box 25)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to soccer, including the Fédération Haïtienne de Football, Haitian national championship, tournament celebrating the reopening of Stade Sylvio Cator in 1997, letter from Racing Club Haiti to the Fédération Haïtienne de Football in 1978.
    - Sports centers, Stade Sylvio Cator, 1996-2002; 1 folder (Box 25)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to sports centers and Stade Sylvio Cator, including the 1997 renovation of the stadium and the construction of sports centers such as Parc Jean-Marie Vincent.
    - Sports, misc., 1987-2002; 1 folder (Box 25)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to sports in general, both in Haiti, in the Haitian diaspora, and abroad. Includes cycling, swimming, basketball, chess, the Olympics, tennis, and other sports.
- Economy, 1977-2003
  - Banking, 1989-2002
    - Banks, 1989-2002; 4 folders (Box 26)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to banks, including Unibank, Banque Nationale de Crédit (BNC), Banque de la République d'Haïti (BRH), Sogebank, Banque de l'Union Haïtienne (BUH), Promobank.
    - Cooperatives and credit unions, 1990-2002; 4 folders (Box 26)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials mainly related to the 2002 cooperatives/credit union schemes, in which thousands of people were defrauded. Includes Coeurs Unis (David Chéry), Conseil National des Coopératives (CNC), Coordination Nationale des Sociétaires Victimes de Coopératives (CONASOVIC). Also contains Radio Haiti materials related to cooperatives and credit unions in general from 1990-2001.
    - Credit, 1996-2001; 1 folder (Box 26)
      See also: Cooperatives and credit unions; Small trades; Informal sector
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to credit, alternative credit, rural credit, microfinance.
    - Banque Haïtienne de Développement, 2001-2002; 1 folder (Box 26)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the Banque Haïtienne de Développement (BHD) scandal of 2002, including the arrest of CEO (président-directeur général) Randolph Voyard for mismanagement of funds, and BHD's bankruptcy.
  - Development, 1978-2003
    - "Champ de réflexions pour un Plan d'Ajustement Structurel Alternatif...", c. 1996-1997; 1 folder (Box 27)
      "Champ de réflexions pour un Plan d'Ajustement Structurel Alternatif (P.A.S.A.) en 3 volets, en vue du Développement endogène d'Haïti" by Webster Pierre.
    - Anti-neoliberalism, 1989-2001; 2 folders (Box 27)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to grassroots actions against debt, austerity measures, IMF, neoliberalism and structural adjustment programs. Includes PAPDA among other groups. Also includes the Coalition Jubilé 2000 to cancel Haiti's external debt.
    - Georges Dabbas, 1982; 1 folder (Box 27)
      Text of "Contribution d'un Patriote Haïtien au Développement Economique et Social de son Pays" by Georges Dabbas; Nouvelliste article about the document.
    - Globalization, 1989-2002; 1 folder (Box 27)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to globalization, global trade, free trade zones, and alternative forms of globalization, including the 2002 Porto Alegre World Social Forum.
    - IDB report, 1978; 1 folder (Box 27)
      Inter-American Development Bank (IDB) report on Haiti.
    - Inter-American Development Bank, 1988; 1995-2003; 2 folders (Box 27)
      See also: Privatization; World Bank; IMF; Anti-neoliberalism; Ministry of Finance
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials (including 1995 contract between the Haitian government and the IDB) related to Inter-American Development Bank (IDB) programs in Haiti, including micro-enterprise, disputes over disbursement of funds, anti-IDB actions.
    - International aid, 1987-2002 (bulk 1995-2002); 3 folders (Box 27)
      See also: Privatization; World Bank; IMF; Anti-neoliberalism; Ministry of Finance; IDB; International Relations; Food security
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to international aid, external aid, food aid (US public law 480), and economic development programs, including the World Trade Organization (WTO/OMC), international donors (USAID, CIDA, FIDA, EU), and NGOs.
    - International Monetary Fund (1 of 2), 1996-2002; 1 folder (Box 27)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the International Monetary Fund (IMF). Includes materials relating to the structural adjustment programs, including several IMF reports and statements. Includes anti-IMF material.
    - International Monetary Fund (2 of 2), 1996-2002; 1 folder (Box 28)
    - Reports, 1986-1987; 1 folder (Box 28)
      Transcript of proceedings from the Caribbean Group for Cooperation in Economic Development, Haiti Subgroup; IDB report; Groupe d'Etudes et de Recherche pour le Développement Economique (GERDEN) report and summary.
    - World Bank, 1995-2002 (bulk 1995-1999); 2 folders (Box 28)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials (primarily World Bank briefs, reports, memos) on World Bank projects and loans in Haiti. Includes anti-World Bank material (from PAPDA and others).
    - World Bank: "Haiti Public Expenditure Review", 1986; 1 folder (Box 28)
      World Bank's "Haiti Public Expenditure Review" from September 29, 1986.
  - Economic policy, 1977-2003
    - Budget, 1977-2002; 1 folder (Box 28)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials (external press, government press releases) relating to Haiti's government budget, deficits, public revenues, parliamentary votes on the budget, budget for development etc.
    - Ministère des Finances, 1977-2002; 5 folders (Box 28)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials (Ministry press releases) relating to the Ministry of Finance under Emmanuel Bros, Leslie Delatour, Léonce Thélusma, Marie-Michèle Rey, Jean-Marie Chérestal, Fred Joseph, and Gustave Faubert. Subjects include budget, industrialization, customs, public revenues, taxes, external aid (IMF, IDB), public administration reform, corruption, and other topics. Folders are arranged chronologically.
    - PAG, 1999; 1 folder (Box 29)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the Plan d'Action Gouvernemental (PAG).
    - Post-coup reconstruction, 1994-1995; 2 folders (Box 29)
      External materials related to Haiti's economic recovery following the 1991-1994 coup years. Includes reports by the Inter-American Development Bank and the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development, speech and decrees by President Jean-Bertrand Aristide, Haitian government publications.
    - Privatization, 1994-1995; 3 folders (Box 29)
      See also: Anti-neoliberalism
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials (including external press, presentations, government contract with UDEP, statements and press releases from labor unions and grassroots organizations) on the privatization of state-owned companies and assets, neoliberal reform and resistance to IMF structural adjustment programs. Includes external press, materials from the Centre pour la Libre Entreprise et la Démocratie/CLED, the Unité de Démocratisation des Enterprises Publiques/UDEP, Aristide's decree creating the UDEP, World Bank/International Finance Corporation invitations for outside firms to bid on Ciment d'Haïti and the Minoterie d'Haïti, the creation of the Conseil de Modernisation des Entreprises Publiques/CMEP, anti-IMF, anti-neoliberal reform declaration from the Haitian delegation to the "50 Years is Enough" conference in Washington DC. State enterprises to be privatized include Ciment d'Haïti, Minoterie d'Haïti, TELECO.
    - Privatization, 1996; 5 folders (Box 29)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials (including external press, report from Concertation pour Haïti, anti-neoliberalism manifesto, pamphlets from CHADEL and Voices for Haiti, Plateforme Haïtienne de Plaidoyer pour un Développement Alternatif/PAPDA publications and press releases) on the privatization of state-owned enterprises and resistance to neoliberal reform and IMF. State enterprises to be "modernized" include Ciment d'Haïti and Teleco.
    - Privatization, 1997; 1 folder (Box 30)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials (including external press, publications from several grassroots groups including PAPDA and labor unions) on the privatization of state assets and increasing popular resistance to neoliberal reform and structural adjustment programs. Public enterprises include Minoterie d'Haïti (now Moulins d'Haïti), Ciment d'Haïti. Includes extensive material on the Conseil de Modernisation des Entreprises Publiques/CMEP, including member Michel Présumé.
    - Privatization, 1998-1999; 1 folder (Box 30)
      See also: APN, Electricity, Public administration, Anti-neoliberalism
      Radio Haiti materials and small amounts of external press relating to privatization, including the Minoterie d'Haïti, the ports and airport (AAN and APN), and electrical company (EDH). Includes CMEP activities, PAPDA resistance. Radio Haiti materials and external materials (including CMEP presentation on the privatization of Ciment d'Haïti, Citibank presentation, press releases by UNDP and others) on privatization, including the port at St. Louis du Sud, Ciment d'Haïti, EDH, airport, APN.
    - Privatization, 2000-2003; 1 folder (Box 30)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials (the legislature's creation of the Coopératives d'Epargne et de Crédit/CEC) relating to privatization of public enteprises and CMEP.
  - Fiscal policy, 1977-2003
    - Customs (1-8), 1990-2003; undated; 8 folders (Box 30)
      See also: DGI; Taxes; Autorité Portuaire Nationale; Contraband
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to customs and the Administration Générale des Douanes. Includes customs revenues, contraband seizures, fraud, customs function in the provinces beyond Port-au-Prince; Haiti-Dominican customs and tariffs. Folders mostly arranged by year.
    - Customs (9-11), 1990-2003; undated; 3 folders (Box 31)
    - DGI, 1995-2002; 5 folders (Box 31)
      See also: Taxes; customs; budget
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the Direction Générale des Impôts (DGI). Includes DGI administration in Port-au-Prince and in the provinces, DGI revenues, corruption with the DGI, revenues, nonpayment of DGI tariffs, identification cards, strikes against DGI, INARA (Institut National de la Réforme Agraire).
    - Taxes, 1977-2002; 1 folder (Box 31)
      See also: Customs; DGI; budget.
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials (petitions and letters, external press, government decrees) related to taxes and tariffs, including peasant and grassroots resistance to taxation.
  - Industry, 1979-2003
    - Association des Industries d'Haïti, 1981; 2 folders (Box 31)
      Two copies of the study "Industries d'Haïti: Situation, Problemes et Perspectives." One copy includes handwritten letter to "J." The letter-writer's name is illegible.
    - Ciment d'Haïti, 1995-2003; 1 folder (Box 32)
      See also: Privatization
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to Ciment d'Haïti, its privatization, and the cement industry in general.
    - Free Trade Zones - Montecristi Corporation, 1986-1989; 2 folders (Box 32)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the Free Trade Zone known as "Hong Kong del Caribe" on the Haitian-Dominican border, at Plantation Dauphin. Includes promotional materials from the Montecristi Corporation, the 1989 contract between the military government under Prosper Avril and the Montecristi Corporation, denunciations by Haitian grassroots organizations including SOFA (Solidarite Fanm Ayisyen), KOTA (Konfederasyon Ouvrye Travayè Ayisyen) and CHANDEL and political parties including MDN (Mobilisation pour le Développement National), Marcel Gilbert; other items.
    - Industry and Private Sector, 1979-1980; 1 folder (Box 32)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to industry, business, international investment, free trade zones, and the private sector. Includes the textile, baseball, laundry detergent industries. Contains letters from the Rawlings baseball company to Jean Dominique and to Lucien Montas of the Nouvelliste, in which Rawlings accuses the jounalists of spreading ostensibly false infomation about the company's dispute with workers. Also includes statutes of Louis Noisin's Le Progrès S.A.
    - Industry and Private Sector, 1987-1991; 2 folders (Box 32)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to industry, business, international investment, free trade zones, and the private sector. External materials include press releases, open letters, and other documents, including a proposal from an American businessman to turn Île de la Tortue into a "new sovereign nation." Contains information relating to the cement industry, PROMINEX, the Enterprise Nationale des Oleagineux (ENAOL), the Cooperative de Production Agricole et Industrielle (COPAIOL), and other factories and industries.
    - Industry and Private Sector, 1995-1999; 1 folder (Box 32)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to industry, business, international investment, free trade zones, and the private sector, including industrial parks (SONAPI) and the Centre pour la Libre Entreprise et la Démocratie (CLED). Includes a 1997 Unité Centrale de Gestion (UCG) report on job creation.
    - Industry and Private Sector, 2000-2003; 1 folder (Box 32)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to industry, business, international investment, and the private sector, including the Centre pour la Libre Entreprise et la Démocratie (CLED), the Association des industries d'Haïti (ADIH),
    - Lists of businesses, 1980s (undated, likely mid 1980s); 1 folder (Box 32)
      List of major businesses in Haiti, including address, owner, years of existence, tax exemption status; second list of major businesses.
    - Minoterie d'Haïti, 1986-1999; 1 folder (Box 32)
      See also: Food security; Privatization
      External materials relating to the Minoterie d'Haïti, including 1986 press released from Yves Volel; communication from 1995 between Jean François Chamblain, Gilbert Léger, Ministère des Finances.
    - Sugar, 1979; 1985-2002; 1 folder (Box 34)
      See also: Agriculture
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about sugar production, including the Darbonne sugar factory in Léogâne. External documents include letter from the Haytian-American Sugar Company (HASCO)'s Grégory Mevs to finance minister Chérestal, World Bank reports. (Note: reports also contain additional information related to non-sugar industry and public enterprises.)
  - Macroeconomics, 1986-2003
    - "Economique au quotidien", 1986-1989; 2 folders (Box 33)
      Radio Haiti's daily economic news, on economic indicators and market conditions within Haiti.
    - Bilans 1997, 1998; 1 folder (Box 33)
      Radio Haiti's summaries and assessments of the 1997 economy in Haiti.
    - Commerce, 1989-2002; 4 folders (Box 33)
      See also: Industry; Agriculture; National production
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to commerce, the Chamber of Commerce and the Ministry of Commerce. Includes exportation and importation, agricultural products, and other subjects.
    - ECOSOF, 1997-2002; 2 folders (Box 33)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to and created by the financial firm ECOSOF and its director, economist Jean-Claude Paulvin. Includes daily economics, inflation, commerce, exchange rates, international aid, national production, and other issues. Note: other ECOSOF materials also appear in other folders, by theme.
    - Exchange rates (1-2), 1995-2003; 2 folders (Box 33)
      Regular, often daily lists of exchange rates between the Haitian gourde and US dollar, by individual bank branch. Includes several copies of the flier for the 2000-2001 writing contest in memory of Jean Dominique, which were used as scratch paper. (Folders arranged by year.)
    - Exchange rates (3-8), 1995-2003; 6 folders (Box 34)
    - General, 1986-2002; 2 folders (Box 34)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the economy in general, including unemployment, general economic indicators and economic policy, and economic crisis. Includes Kesner Pharel's Groupe Croissance.
    - Inflation and Lavichè, 1986-2003; 5 folders (Box 35)
      See also: Minimum wage; Fuel; Exchange rates